<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body xml:id="Excerpta_comm">
         <div>
            <head>Excerpta comment</head>
            <p>´ ] The biblical text seems to be the source for at least some terms of the excerpt
               concerning the names used to define pagan cult objects. In the usual list, some quite
               unfavorable words appear. Indeed, the pair προσοχθίσματα (‘offences’) and βδελύγματα
               (‘abominations’) recalls LXX De. 7, 25‒6, and, shortly after, ἔργα χειρῶν (‘works of
               hands’) undoubtedly echoes LXX Ps. 113; in both of these passages, pagan idols are
               presented in an extremely negative light, something that an attentive reader would
               surely not have failed to notice. The excerpt concludes with a suggestion on how to
               refer to the great number of pagan gods: δῆμον and πολυαρχίαν θεῶν. The expression is
               very similar – indeed, it appears almost literally extracted – to what Theodore
               Metochites (1270‒1332) says in one of his orations for Saint Demetrius the Great
               Martyr (Or. 4, 12, 124 Kaltsogianni-Polemis) δῆμον θεῶν ἄτακτον καὶ πολυαρχίαν, καὶ
               θροῦν ἄλογον (“a confused crowd of gods and a polyarchy, and an senseless din”). If
               the source here is truly the writing of Theodore Metochites, it would be a citation
               of an author substantially contemporary with, or slightly preceding, the drafting of
               the two codices that have come down to us. It would follow that y should be dated
               later than the composition of the Byzantine scholar's oration, the precise date of
               which is unfortunately not known.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
